A Finding Aid to the Abbott Handerson Thayer and Thayer Family Papers, 1851-1999 (bulk 1881-1950), in the Archives of American Art AAA.thayabbo
Archives of American Art
Abbott Handerson Thayer and Thayer Family papers
bulk 1881-1950
1851-1999
AAA.thayabbo
Archives of American Art
4.9 Linear feet
The papers of painter and naturalist, Abbott Handerson Thayer, and the Thayer family date from 1851 to 1999, with the bulk of the material dating from 1881 to 1950, and measure 4.9 linear feet. Thayer's painting career, interest in concealing coloration (camouflage) in nature, and relationships with artists, patrons, family, and friends are documented through correspondence, writings, scattered legal and financial records, printed materials, and a scrapbook. Photographs are of Thayer, his family, studio, and friends, including artists. The collection also contains family papers created by his second wife, Emma Beach Thayer, his son Gerald, his daughters Mary and Gladys, and Gladys' husband David Reasoner, who managed Thayer's estate after his death.
Thayer, Abbott Handerson
Provenance
The Abbott Handerson Thayer and Thayer Family papers were donated in 1999 by Abbott Thayer's great-grandson, John Plunket, who received the papers from his mother Jean Reasoner Plunket. In 2005 Bruce Gimelson donated additional material purchased from relatives of Emma Beach Thayer.
Separated Material
Anne Whiting, a niece of Abbott Handerson Thayer, loaned a diary kept by Thayer, a "Family Record" written by William Henry Thayer, correspondence, printed material, and photographs for microfilming in 1971. These items were returned to Whiting after microfilming and are available to researchers on reel 48. In 1985 Jean Reasoner Plunket, Thayer's granddaughter, loaned original artwork by Thayer which was returned to her after microfilming on reel 3417. These materials are not included in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds several collections related to Abbott Handerson Thayer. These include research material on Abbott Handerson Thayer and other artists, 1895-1990, donated by Thomas B. Brumbaugh; the Abbott Handerson Thayer letter and drawings to Caroline Peddle Ball, circa 1890-1893; "The Drawings of Abbott Thayer", by Elizabeth Robins Pennell, circa 1921; and the Nelson and Henry C. White research material, 1898-1978, which includes many letters, photographs, and other material originally belonging to the Thayer family.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Abbott Handerson Thayer and the Thayer family in the Archives of American Art were digitized in 2007. The bulk of the papers have been scanned and total 10074 images.
Types of materials that have not been digitized include certain printed materials and financial records, unidentifed photographs and photographs of artwork, and certain items related to others, as noted in the folder lists for each series.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Glass plate negative is housed separately and closed to researchers.
Biographical Note
Abbott Handerson Thayer (1849-1921) was born in Boston to Dr. William Henry Thayer and Ellen Handerson Thayer. After his birth his family moved to Woodstock, Vermont, and in 1855 settled in Keene, New Hampshire. As a child Thayer developed a love of nature that was encouraged by his close family, which included three sisters, Ellen, Margaret, and Susan. At the age of fifteen he was sent to the Chauncy Hall School in Boston, and while there he met Henry D. Morse, an amateur animal painter. Under Morse's instruction Abbott developed his skill in painting birds and other wildlife and began painting animal portraits on commission. In 1867 he moved to Brooklyn, New York and attended the Brooklyn Academy of Design where he studied under J. B. Whittaker for two years. In 1868 he began showing his work at the National Academy of Design and enrolled there in 1870, studying under Lemuel Wilmarth. He met many emerging artists during this period, including his future first wife, Kate Bloede and his close friend, Daniel Chester French. Thayer became part of progressive art circles, showing his work at the newly formed Society of American Artists, while continuing to develop his skill as an animal and landscape painter.
Thayer and Kate Bloede were married in 1875. They moved to Paris and he studied at the École des Beaux-Arts, first under Henri Lehmann, and then with Jean-Léon Gérome. While in Europe he befriended fellow artists Everton Sainsbury, Thomas Millie Dow, George de Forest Brush, and Dwight Tryon. His daughter Mary was born in 1876 and his son William Henry in 1878. The family returned to America in 1879 and settled in his parent's home in Brooklyn, where he changed his focus to portraits. After the tragic deaths of William Henry in 1880 and of their second son, Ralph Waldo, in 1881, the family led a migratory existence living in various parts of New England. In 1881 while living in Nantucket they met Emmeline (Emma) Beach (1850-1924) who would become close friends with Abbott and Kate and would be known as "Addie" to the family. In 1883 their son Gerald was born and in 1886 their daughter Gladys was born. In 1887 Thayer settled his family in Keene, New Hampshire, and began teaching a small group of students. Around this time his wife began suffering from severe depression and went to a sanatorium in 1888. She died in 1891 and that fall Thayer married Emma Beach who had helped to care for him and his children during his wife's illness.
Despite family tragedies, Thayer became a leader in the New York art world during the 1880s and 1890s. He was a successful portraitist and painted allegorical figures of angels, women, and children, which were popular among collectors of this period, including his patrons Charles Lang Freer and John Gellatly. He often used his children as models, especially his eldest daughter, Mary.
In the late 1880s one of Thayer's students, Mary Amory Greene, built a house and studio for the Thayer family on her land in Dublin, New Hampshire, and in 1901 the family settled there permanently. Many of Thayer's artist friends lived nearby, such as Richard Meryman and George de Forest Brush, and the Thayer family frequently entertained prominent visitors such as Edward Waldo Emerson and Samuel Clemens. Abbott Thayer taught painting to his children, and Gerald and Gladys both became artists and art educators. Gladys married David Reasoner, a student of Abbott Thayer who later became his assistant. Other students of Thayer included Rockwell Kent, Ben Foster, Barry Faulkner, and Louis Agassiz Fuertes.
Greatly influenced by transcendentalism and the spirituality of nature, Thayer again began to paint landscapes, especially of nearby Mount Monadnock. He was very interested in the study of protective coloration in the wild, and was an advocate for nature conservation and bird sanctuaries. He published the book Concealing Coloration in the Animal Kingdom in 1909 with his son Gerald, but encountered much resistance to his theories. Thayer also wrote about how his camouflage theories could be applied to military warships and uniforms. These theories failed to gain widespread government interest and after suffering from nervous exhaustion, he spent the rest of his life painting landscapes at his home in Dublin, until his death in 1921.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and naturalist, Abbott Handerson Thayer, and the Thayer family date from 1851 to 1999, with the bulk of the material dating from 1881 to 1950, and measure 4.9 linear feet. Thayer's painting career, interest in concealing coloration in nature, and relationships with artists, patrons, family, and friends are documented through correspondence, writings, scattered legal and financial records, printed materials, and a scrapbook. Photographs are of Thayer, his family, studio, and friends, including artists. The collection also contains family papers created by his second wife, Emma Beach Thayer, his son Gerald, his daughters Mary and Gladys, and Gladys' husband David Reasoner, who managed Thayer's estate after his death.
Scattered Biographical Material includes a brief autobiographical statement and chronology by Abbott Thayer, lists of artworks by Abbott Thayer and Gladys Thayer Reasoner, and biographical information about Thayer's granddaughter, Jean Reasoner Plunket. Two linear feet of family correspondence includes Abott Thayer's correspondence with patrons Charles L. Freer and John Gellatly; with many artists, several of whom were close friends, including Samuel Colman, Thomas Millie Dow, Daniel Chester French, Richard Meryman, Everton Sainsbury, Louis Agassiz Fuertes, and E. M. Taber; and former students, such as Ben Foster and Barry Faulkner; and with other friends, many of them prominent members of society, such as Samuel Clemens, Royal Cortissoz, Edward Waldo Emerson, and Stanford White. Also found is Thayer's correspondence with scientists and naturalists discussing his theories on protective coloration in nature. Correspondence of his second wife Emma Beach Thayer, his first wife, Kate Bloede Thayer, his daughter, Gladys Thayer Reasoner, her husband and executor of Thayer's estate, David Reasoner, and other family members are also included in the papers.
Writings and notes by Thayer record his thoughts on concealing coloration, nature, restoration of artwork, and other topics. Writings by others include those by Emma Beach Thayer, daughters Mary and Gladys, and Thayer scholars. The collection also contains correspondence of David Reasoner and other family members, as well as financial and legal documents regarding the estate of Abbott Handerson Thayer and Emma Beach Thayer. Additional financial and legal material includes ledgers, accounts statements, bills, a patent granted to Thayer and Gerome Brush, legal agreements, property deeds, and a map of Thayer's property.
Printed material include books, including one written by Theodore Roosevelt in response to Thayer's book on concealing coloration. Also found are newspaper and magazine clippings, and exhibition announcements and catalogs. Photographs are of Abbott Thayer, his wife Emma; his studio and home in Dublin, New Hampshire; friends, including Rockwell Kent and Ralph Waldo Emerson; and of unidentified people. Artwork includes a few drawings by Thayer, drawings and paintings by his children, and sketchbooks belonging to David Reasoner and Jean Reasoner Plunket. The collection also includes one large scrapbook kept by David Reasoner documenting Abbott Thayer's artwork.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 10 series. Glass plate negative is housed separately and closed to researchers.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1878 - circa 1966 (Box 1; 7 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1867-1987 (Box 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, 1888-1945 (Box 3; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 4: Estate Papers, 1921-1954 (Box 3-4; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 5: Other Financial Records, 1889-1957 (Box 4; 7 folders)
Series 6: Legal Records, 1891-1927 (Box 4; 4 folders)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1851, 1896-1999 (Box 4-5; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1861-1933 (Box 5, MGP 2; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 9: Artwork, 1887 - circa 1940s (Box 5-6, 8; 8 folders)
Series 10: Scrapbook, circa 1910-1920 (Box 7; 0.3 linear feet)
Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910; Colman, Samuel, 1832-1920; Cortissoz, Royal, 1869-1948; Dow, Thomas Millie; Emerson, Edward Waldo, 1844-1930; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882; Faulkner, Barry, 1881-1966; Foster, Ben, 1852-1926; Freer, Charles Lang, 1856-1919; French, Daniel Chester, 1850-1931; Fuertes, Louis Agassiz, 1874-1927; Gellatly, John, 1853-1931; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971; Meryman, Richard Sumner, 1881-1963; Plunket, Jean Reasoner; Reasoner, David; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Sainsbury, Everton; Taber, E. M.; Thayer, Emma B., 1850-1924; Thayer, Gerald Handerson, 1883-1939; Thayer, Gladys, 1886 or 7-1945; Thayer, Kate Bloede; Thayer, Mary; White, Stanford, 1853-1906; Art and camouflage; Camouflage (Biology); Naturalists; Painters--New Hampshire--Dublin; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Biographical Material, 1878-circa 1966; Series 1; (Box 1; 9 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes a brief autobiographical statement by Abbott Thayer and a chronology of his artwork and family activities from 1880 to 1921. Also found is the French birth certificate for Thayer's son William Henry Thayer, newspaper obituaries for Emma Beach Thayer, and lists of artworks by Abbott Thayer and Gladys Thayer Reasoner. A biographical sketch written by David Reasoner about the early life of his daughter, Jean Reasoner Plunket, and Jean's genealogy research on the Thayer and Plunket families are filed here.
  - Abbott Handerson Thayer Autobiographical Summary and Chronology, 1907, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbott Handerson Thayer, Exhibition Tickets, 1897, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Emma Beach Thayer Obituaries, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Birth Certificate for William Henry Thayer, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lists of Artwork by Abbott Handerson Thayer, circa 1922 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lists of Portraits Painted by Gladys Thayer Reasoner, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gladys Thayer Reasoner's Address Book, circa 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jean Reasoner Plunket Biographical Sketches, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Genealogy for Thayer and Plunket Families, circa 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1867-1987; Series 2; (Box 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
  Personal and professional correspondence of the Thayer family is found in this series. The bulk of the correspondence belongs to Abbott Handerson Thayer and his second wife Emma Beach Thayer, although several folders are for Thayer's first wife Kate Bloede Thayer. Correspondence is also found for Thayer's daughter Gladys Thayer Reasoner and her husband David Reasoner and other family members, including Mary Thayer Birch, Gerald Thayer, and Jean Reasoner Plunket.
  Arrangement note
  The Correspondence series has been arranged primarily by individual family member or general correspondence into 6 subseries:
  Subseries 2.1: Abbott Handerson Thayer Correspondence, 1881-1921
  Subseries 2.2: Emma Beach Thayer Correspondence, 1865-1924
  Subseries 2.3: Kate Bloede Thayer Correspondence, 1881-1889
  Subseries 2.4: Gladys Thayer Reasoner Correspondence, 1907-1943
  Subseries 2.5: David Reasoner Correspondence, 1918-1954
  Subseries 2.6: General Correspondence, 1883-1987
  - Abbott Handerson Thayer Correspondence, 1881-1921; 2.1
    Abbott Handerson Thayer's correspondence consists primarily of letters to Thayer, but includes a few handwritten copies or drafts of his outgoing letters. Found here are numerous personal letters to and from family members, including his daughters Mary and Gladys (Galla), his son Gerald (Gra), and his wife Emma (also known as Addie), as well as nephews, nieces, sisters, cousins, and other extended family. There is correspondence with his patrons Charles L. Freer and John Gellatly; with many artists, several of whom were close friends, including Samuel Colman, Thomas Millie Dow, Daniel Chester French, Richard Meryman, Everton Sainsbury, Louis Agassiz Fuertes, and E. M. Taber; and former students, such as Ben Foster and Barry Faulkner; with other friends, many of them prominent members of society, such as Samuel Clemens, Royal Cortissoz, Edward Waldo Emerson, and Stanford White. A large amount of Thayer's correspondence concerns his research on protective coloration in nature and the publication of his book Concealing Coloration in the Animal Kingdom. To pursue and defend his theories on concealing coloration, especially as applied to birds, he corresponded with many notable naturalists, biologists, ornithologists, and collection curators. Most notable is his extensive correspondence with Sir Edwin Bagnall Poulton, a British zoologist, and draft letters to Theodore Roosevelt, in defense and promotion of his work. He corresponded with many, including Franklin D. Roosevelt, then the Assistant Secretary of the Navy, and the War Office in London, promoting his theory on the value of concealing coloration for warships and the military. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent and chronologically within each folder.
    - Allen, Francis, 1909-1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - A, 1904-1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Adams, Charles C.
      Adams, Jenny S.
      Allen, John E.
      American Academy of Arts and Letters
    - Bartsch, Paul, 1914-1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Beach, Ella, circa 1891-1914 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Beach, Moses S. & Chloe, 1882-circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Beach, Violet, 1890-circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Birch, Fred & Mary Thayer, 1897-1914 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bowditch, Vincent Y., 1883, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Brewster, William, 1902-1911 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Ba-Be, 1890s-1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Baird, J. A.
      Barton, C. Vanderbilt
      Battin, Benjamin
      Bayard, Fairfax
      Beach, Charles
      Beatty, John W.
      Bell, Arthur G.
      Bell, F. Jeffrey
      Benson, Frank
    - Bi-Bu, 1902-1921 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Birch, Elsie
      Birch, Mrs. (Fred Birch's mother)
      Blashfield, Edwin Howland
      Bloede, Victor G.
      Bonnat, Mr.
      Braun, John F.
      Brenton, Albert G.
      Brown, H. S.
      Bruce, Charles M.
      Buffalo Fine Arts Academy
      Bureau des Inventions, Ministere de l'Armement
      Burlingham, L. L.
      Burroughs, John
    - Clemens, Samuel L., 1905-1909 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Colman, Samuel, 1913, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Cortissoz, Royal, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Ca-Cl, 1897-1918 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Cabot, Mrs. Arthur (Susie)
      Cabot, Elise Pumpelly
      Cabot, W. B.
      Calkins, Professor
      Carnegie, Andrew
      Carr, Albert
      Cattell, J.
      Channing, Anna K.
      Cheney, Frederick E.
      Churchill, Winston
      Clark, Austin H.
      Clark, Edgar
      Clark, John S.
      Clarke, Samuel F.
    - Co-Cu, 1911-1918 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Cockerell, Theo. D. A.
      Codair, Ernest W.
      Coffin, William A.
      Contant, R. B.
      Coolidge, Dr. A.
      Coolidge, John T.
      Cooper, Susan Fenimore
      Crandall, L. S.
      Cunard S. S. Line
    - Dow, Thomas Millie, 1883-1896 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
    - D, 1910-1918 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Davis, Livingston
      Dewing, Thomas Wilmer
      Dwight, Daniel A.
    - Eckstorm, Fannie, 1906-1917 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Emerson, Edward Waldo, 1910-1914 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - E, 1897-1915 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Endicott, William
      Ewart, Professor
    - Forbes, Alexander, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Foster, Ben, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Freer, Charles L., 1893-1916 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - French, Daniel Chester, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Fa-Fi, 1904-1921 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Farmborough, Percy W.
      Faulkner, Barry
      Fenn, Roger
      Fischer, Dr. Martin H.
      Fisher, Ned
    - Fo-Fu, 1907-1916 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Forbush, Edward Howe
      Forest and Stream
      Franck, Peter
      Fuertes, Louis Agassiz
    - Gellatly, John, 1910-1918 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - G, 1893-1917 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Gérôme, Jean-Léon
      Grave, Caswell
      Green, H. S.
      Greene, Mary Amory
      Grovenor, Gilbert H.
      Guthrie, W. N.
    - Handerson, Esther, 1889-1895 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - H, 1911-1919 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      Hardy, Walter M.
      Hatch, Rob
      Hawthorne, Charles W.
      Hazen, John D.
      Hemenway, Mr.
      Hill, Mrs.
      Hodge, C. F.
      Holbrook, Mrs. Frederick
      Hutchins, Professor
    - James, William & Alice, 1910-1920 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - J-K, 1903, 1914-1916 (Box 1, Folder 43)
      James, Angela?
      Johnson, R. U.
      Kurtz, W. M.
    - Longley, W. H., 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - L, 1899-1920 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Lankester, Edwin Ray
      Latham, Mrs. C. F.
      Lay, Wilfrid
      Leicester
      Library of Congress
      Life magazine
      Lillie, Frank R.
      Lucas, Frederic A.
    - Meryman, Richard (Wig), 1916-1919 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Ma, 1892, 1908-1919 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      Macbeth Galleries
      Mackintosh, Henry S.
      Macmillan Company
      MacVeagh, Franklin
      Manship, Paul
      Marshall, Guy A. K.
      Masefield, John
      Mathewson, Dr.
      Mayer, Alfred G.
      Mayor's Committee on Cultivation of Vacant Lots by the Unemployed
    - Me-Mu, 1896-1924 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Mead, Teddy
      Mercur, Dr. William H.
      Merriam, Clinton Hart
      Minnigerode, C. Powell
      Moloney, Governor
      Momber, E. A.
      Morris, Mr.
    - N-O, 1913-1921 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      National Academy of Design
      Olcott, Adeline Cheney
      Old Colony Trust Company
      Oldys, Henry
    - Poulton, Sir Edward Bagnall, 1898-1915; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
    - Poulton, Sir Edward Bagnall, Undated Letters, circa 1898-1915; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-54)
    - P, 1902-1915 (Box 1, Folder 55)
      Packard, Alpheus Spring
      Parker, G. H.
      Patten, Mary C.
      Peabody, Francis Greenwood
      Pepper, Charles H.
      Perabo, Ernst
      Perkins, Katrine C.
      Pocock, R. I.
      Psychological Laboratory, Cornell University
      Putnam, A. P.
    - Reasoner, Gladys Thayer, 1897-1919 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore, circa 1910 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Q-R, 1903-1917 (Box 1, Folder 59)
      Quelch, Joe
      Rand, Mr.
      Reusch, Hans & Helga
      Rice, James Henry
      Richards, Patty
      Robbins, Reginald C.
      Robinson, B. L.
      Robinson, Scott
    - Sainsbury, Everton, 1876-1882 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Sa-Sl, 1896-1922 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      Sackett, Edith S.
      Sainsbury, Harrington
      Sears, Sara C.
      Secretary of the Admiralty
      Shelden, C. S.
      Shurtleff, Roswell Morse
      Shurtleff, William H.
      Slack, Julia L.
      Sloane, William M.
    - Sm-St, 1899-1919 (Box 1, Folder 62)
      Smith, William Lord
      Southwick, E. B.
      Stephens, T. C.
      Stillman, Clara
    - Taber, E. M. & Frances F. Holt (Taber's sister), 1890-1913; (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 63-65)
    - Thayer, Emma Beach, 1881-1919; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 66-67)
    - Thayer, Emma Beach, Undated Letters, circa 1881-1919 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - T-V, 1890, 1907-1916 (Box 1, Folder 69)
      Thayer, David
      Thayer, Gerald
      Tiffany, Louis Comfort
      Tryon, Dwight W.
      Van Norden, Ottomar H.
      Von Wittenburg, Marie
    - War Office, London, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Whelpley, Jay & Philip, 1904-1917 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Wa-We, 1896-1918 (Box 1, Folder 72)
      Walker, H. O.
      Wallace, Alfred R.
      Walton, Blanche W.
      Warren, Gretchen
      Watkins & Doncaster
      Webster, Arthur Gordon
      Weigels, Mrs.
      Weld, George F.
      Wellesley College
      Wentworth, N.
    - Wh-Wy, 1882-1917 (Box 1, Folder 73)
      White, Stanford
      Wilcox, W. D.
      Wild Life Protection League of America
      Wilson, Woodrow
      Wyeth, N. C.
      Wylie, J. E.
    - Y-Z, 1889, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 74)
      Yale University
      Zuler?, H. Morris
    - Unidentified Correspondents, 1891-1918 (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Unidentified Correspondents, Fragments, circa 1880-1920 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Emma Beach Thayer Correspondence, 1865-1924; 2.2